Hey, בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf is ע"ה, Ayin Hey,
and we pick up at the bottom of ע"ד עמוד ב׳, Ayin
Daled amud bet, very interesting גמרא Gemara we’re in right now about
what constitutes satisfying of תנאים, tna’im, of conditions. According to the משנה,
Mishnah, the way the גמרא Gemara reads the משנה, Mishnah, somebody says,
"give me my cloak." רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
says that if the cloak is lost, just give the money. And
the רבנן Rabbanan say, "no, you have to give the cloak itself."
And then the גמרא Gemara compared that to the question of are
you allowed to say—if you say,
"you give me 200 זוז," zuz, are you allowed to say אחולי
מחילנא לך, achulei machilna lach, which A is a possibility—can you just
waive the תנאי? tnai? Or B, the way the גמרא’ס Gemara’s phrasing
it is you can’t waive the תנאי, tnai, but can you say,
"look, it’s just about my הנאה hana’ah and I’ll treat it as
if I received it"? So we saw a parallel case by נדרים
nedarim where that does work.
And here, though, the גמרא Gemara says it might be different, because
it’s very interesting—you could in both these cases say the same thing,
but in one case we translate it as that it’s 200 זוז
zuz defined as my הנאה, hana’ah, that’s the נדר neder case, as
opposed to 200 זוז zuz defined as "you have to suffer," maybe,
and my הנאה. hana’ah. So, and maybe if that’s what the person
had in mind by the גט get case, he’s not in a
position to say it’s like the תנאי’ס tnai’s been satisfied because the
other person still hasn't suffered. So, very interesting how we consider what
constitutes satisfying that תנאי tnai about what might have been your thoughts
in terms of what that תנאי tnai was about. Yes, Michael.
Just to make sure, all that stuff about the suffering and that,
that was a whole thing was only if he gave her the
גט get first, right?
Yeah, yeah, yeah, all of
that, yeah, if
he’s blackmailing her he can do whatever he wants—I mean, not he
can do whatever he wants, but you know what I mean, like
it’s not a הלכתית halachic discussion. Here the question is the גט
get was given and that it’s on a תנאי, tnai, and is
the תנאי tnai satisfied? So now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
We are on the bottom of ע"ד עמוד ב׳. Ayin Daled amud
bet.
ההוא גברא. Hahu gavra.
It’s about one, two, three, four, five... about twelve lines before the
lines get wide. End of the line, ההוא גברא דאמר ליה לאריסיה.
Hahu gavra de-amar lei le-ariseh. Lines start with the word לאריסיה le-ariseh
right by like this little marginal note.
Yes, צמח לגרסינן, Tzemach legarsinan, right. ההוא גב-, Hahu gav-, little marginal
note in the right-hand margin there. Okay. ההוא גברא דאמר ליה לאריסיה.
Hahu gavra de-amar lei le-ariseh. A certain person said to his sharecropper,
כולי עלמא דלו תלת דופסא ואכלי ריבעא. Kulei alma daly telat davsa
ve-achli riva.
All of the sharecroppers irrigate the field, water the field, three times
in the course of the year and they’re entitled to a quarter
of the produce. את דלי ארבע ואכול תילתא. At daly arba ve-achol
tilta.
I’m going to make you a deal with you. I want you
to irrigate it four times but in exchange you’ll actually get a
third, you’ll get more of the produce. What’s the difference between a
fourth and a third quickly, everybody? One-twelfth. So much for your math.
Okay, all right.
Pop quiz. Okay, anyway, so that’s the deal and he agreed to
it.
So
he’s entitled to a third provided
that—את דלי ארבע ואכול תילתא. At daly arba ve-achol tilta.
לסוף, Lesof, at the end, אתא מיטרא. ata mitra. Rain came and
it didn’t need the extra irrigation. Instead of him having to irrigate
it rained, it would have been counter-productive to irrigate after that rain.
אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, says רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, הא
לא דלא. ha lo dala. Look, he didn't do what he agreed
to, he’s not entitled to that extra amount. He didn’t do the
extra irrigation. רבא אמר, Rava amar, רבא Rava says, הא לא איצטריכא.
ha lo itztrecha. No, it wasn’t required. So I—it’s like the תנאי
tnai is satisfied because the תנאי tnai was to achieve an end
result and the end result was satisfied. So, that’s—it’s like it’s satisfied.
So the גמרא Gemara says, לימא רב יוסף סבר רבנן ורבא סבר
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Leimar Rav Yosef savar Rabbanan ve-Rava savar Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel. Let’s say this is sort of like the רבנן
Rabbanan and רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says money is equal to the
cloak. So here the God rain, God causing it to rain is
equal to me raining it, in the end you got what you
wanted or you got some equivalent of what you wanted. And the
other one says no, it has to be the exact way that
the תנאי tnai was formulated. So the גמרא Gemara says, no, ותסברא,
ve-tisbra, does that make sense? וקיימא לן הלכתא כוותיה דרבא. Ve-kayma lan
hilchata kevata de-Rava. We generally rule that the ruling is according to
רבא, Rava, which would mean that we would say that the תנאי
tnai was satisfied here. רבא Rava said הא לא איצטריכא ליה ha
lo itztrecha lei in the case of the irrigation. But also, thank
you so much, ובהא אין הלכה כרבן שמעון בן גמליאל. u-ve-ha ein
halacha ke-Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. We’re going to say in a few
lines that we don't rule like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel by the cloak. So clearly you can rule that by
the cloak money is not a substitute, but by the rain came,
by the irrigation case the rain worked. So there has to be
a different logic in those two cases. So the גמרא Gemara says,
אלא לעולם כרבנן. Ela le-olam ke-Rabbanan. Fine, you’re right, we have to
say we go like the רבנן Rabbanan that money is not a
substitute for the cloak. רב יוסף כרבנן. Rav Yosef ke-Rabbanan. So רב
יוסף Rav Yosef is simply the רבנן, Rabbanan, you gotta do exactly
what you said, you didn’t do what you said. ורבא אמר לך,
Ve-Rava amar lach, and רבא Rava will say to you, רבנן... Rabbanan...
ורבא אמר לך. Ve-Rava amar lach. אנא דאמרי אפילו כרבנן. Ana de'amri
afilu keRabbanan.
I could say like the Rabbis by the cloak. עד כאן לא
קאמרי רבנן התם אלא דלציעורא קמכוון. Ad kan lo kaamri Rabbanan hatam
ella delitzira kamichavein.
Again, when do you interpret that תנאי tenai means exactly this and
when do you interpret that substitutes are allowed? So when it's the
case of גיטין, Gittin, we're going to say that it's not just
about what he gets. He wants to make certain demands of her.
And therefore, דלציעורא קמכוון. delitzira kamichavein. Now, this is so funny because
why is there more לציעורא letzira to hand back a cloak than
to, you know, than to go to my bank account and get
out $200 or whatever? You know, but if anything, you should say
there he makes more demands because it's his cloak and it's something
personal. But anyway, the גמרא Gemara is going to say by גיטין
Gittin we're going to be predisposed to read all תנאים tenaim as
very precise, because essentially the point is not to give her latitude.
That if you were to ask him, do you allow for substitutions?
Then the, you know, if you were to try to get into
his דעת, da'at, the answer would be no, why should I allow
for substitutions? I'm trying to give her a hard time. No matter
what it is. So if by גיטין Gittin we should read all
the תנאי tenai right, presumably no matter what it is. Meaning, let's
say he said that I want you to give me $200, you
know, that's stored in the, you know, in the cookie jar and
she gave him $200 stored somewhere else or whatever. Presumably we're just
going to say that it's always דווקא davka by גיטין Gittin because
he's not going to, he דווקא davka wants to make her life
hard. So if he says a תנאי, tenai, we're not going to
give any latitude. Whereas by other things, especially this, which is all
about money, it's all about earning money, you know, the field and
about what he's going to profit from the field, so it's all
about הנאה. hana'ah. So of course, so we should assume that any
alternative would be just as good.
Okay, so you interpret it to mean give הרצאה. hartza'ah.
Yeah, that's exactly what it means.
Uh-huh, so with the jacket, it would be the same thing?
Yeah, well that's the point, by the jacket, it's only the jacket.
Because I want the jacket, I don't want a substitute and have
to go out and buy a substitute?
No, no, I want, I want to make more demands on her.
Meaning, it's not about my צער, tza'ar, right? It's like by, by
the גט, get, he's trying to make demands on her. So we
don't assume that any תנאי tenai allows for latitude and allows for
substitution.
So לחפצא lecheftza is irrelevant
really? That's the way...
It's about the relationship, exactly.
Maybe the opposite, right? קידושין Kiddushin would be the opposite?
What? קידושין Kiddushin might be, but it depends, maybe she's making demands,
but presumably right, okay. דלציעורא קמכוון. delitzira kamichavein. אבל הכא משום ארווחא,
Aval hacha mishum arrucha, here
he's a businessman, not personal. By גט get it's personal, this is
business. והא לא איצטריך, Veha lo itztarich, and it wasn't necessary. Okay.
Of course you could say he wouldn't want to pay the guy
extra if he wouldn't have to, right, I always thought about that
too, but...
But what's he say?
But it's his job and then they...
I don't know what to say, it's a very good question. All
right, now the גמרא Gemara says as
follows: תנן התם. tenan hatam. We taught over there in ערכין. Arachin.
בראשונה, Barishonah, we're going to move a little bit away from what,
what constitutes satisfying the תנאי, tenai, but to an obviously related topic.
בראשונה היה נטמן יום שנים עשר חודש כדי שיהא חלוט לו. Barishonah
hayah nitman yom shenem asar chodesh kedei sheyehe chalut lo.
So a person who buys a house in a walled city during
the time that the יובל Yovel is נוהג, noheig, the seller has
a year to buy it back. And if the seller doesn't buy
it back within the year, then the sale becomes permanent. So what
would happen would be on the last day of the year, okay,
the purchaser would go and hide, so that the seller could not
find him and give him back the money. Now, of course, you
know, the seller might want to give him back the money anytime
during the year, but the point is I guess that it takes,
if the seller had to sell his house, he was hard up
for funds, so it might take him till the very, very end
till he could get some money back together to buy it back.
So what they would do is that they would go and hide
כדי שיהא חלוט לו, kedei sheyehe chalut lo, that the house would
be permanently sold to them.
I would have thought it would be the opposite, you know, that...
whatever. התקין הלל הזקן, Hitkin Hillel HaZaken, remember good old Hillel, who
was also מתקן metakein by the פרוזבול? pruzbul? A lot of תקנות
takkanot in the context of יובל Yovel was, you know, Hillel. Anyway,
התקין הלל הזקן שיהא חולש מעותיו ללשכה. Hitkin Hillel HaZaken sheyehe cholesh
ma'otav lalishkah.
That you should basically throw your money, you know, deposit your money
in the, in the like, in the chamber, meaning presumably in like
the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, I think it presumably means בית המקדש,
Beis HaMikdash, which is funny, then everybody has to travel to ירושלים.
Yerushalayim. Right, unless לשכה lishkah means some local לשכה. lishkah. והיה שובר
את הדלת, Vehayah shover es hadeleth, and go ahead and break in
the door if you're the original owner, ונכנס, venichnas, and reclaim your
house. Okay, ואימת שירצה הלה יבא ויטול מעותיו. Ve'eimas sheyirtzeh halah yavo
veyittol ma'osav. You say, yeah, I paid you back, the money's been
deposited for you in a bank account, the money has been deposited
for you at בית דין, Beis Din, and yeah, I'm sorry you
weren't around for me to give it to you, but now I've
paid you back. Okay, ואמר רבא, Ve'amar Rava, now Rava says, מתקנתו
של הלל. mitakkanaso shel Hillel. So that's all interesting, why is it
relevant for us? נשמע, Nishma, so from the Hillel's תקנה takkana we
can infer: הרי זה גיטך על מנת שתתני לי מאתים זוז. Harei
zeh gittech al menas shetitni li masayim zuz. This is your גט
get on the condition you give me 200 זוז. zuz. ונתנה לו
מדעתו מגורשת. Venasanah lo mada'ato megureshes. If she gives it to him
and he agrees to accept the money, she's divorced. על כרחו, Al
koro, let's say he's trying to run away from her. Good, I
got the 200 זוז, zuz, and he's running away. No, no, no,
I'm not going to let you fulfill the תנאי. tenai. And she
throws the money at him let’s say, okay, puts the money on
his in the house. And he says, I don’t want to take
it. אינה מגורשת. Einah m’goreshet. It’s not good. Yeah, he wants to
still stay married, he changed his mind, I mean, he already was
with the 200 זוז, zuz, he thought she wasn’t going to get
it, he thought he would just torture her, she
managed to get the 200 זוז, zuz, he’s not happy with the
situation. So it’s a buyer, as if the buyer would have run
away to hide?
The buyer ran away. The buyer. אינה מגורשת, Einah m’goreshet, she’s not
divorced. Okay, now, which means he
can't keep the money though, right?
Well, if he didn’t accept the money, he didn’t accept the money.
מכדי אצטריכא ליה להלל לתקוני נתינה בעל כרחו דהויא לה נתינה? Michdi
itztricha lei l’Hillel l’takuni nethina ba’al korcho de’havya lei nethina? It doesn't
matter, he didn't accept it. מכדי אצטריכא ליה להלל לתקוני נתינה בעל
כרחו דהויא לה נתינה? Michdi itztricha lei l’Hillel l’takuni nethina ba’al korcho
de’havya lei nethina? So the question is, what was הלל Hillel necessary
for? Now if you ask me, what the גמרא Gemara is going
to say is, it sounds like what he was necessary for was
that the guy wasn't present, that in order to be an act
of giving it to him he had to be physically present. But
the גמרא Gemara is saying there’s two things going on. A, he
wasn't physically present and B, he did not want to accept the
money. So the גמרא Gemara understands that הלל’s Hillel חידוש chiddush was
that we’re going to treat it that giving him the money even
against his will it’s like you gave it to him, which means
that the implicit assumption is that the normal rule is that giving
somebody something against their will is not like you gave it to
them. Okay, now of course who says the הלכה halacha is the
same when we're dealing with a תנאי tnai that you created and
when we're dealing with like a transaction that the תורה, Torah, you
know, recognized? Meaning if I make a תנאי, tnai, the תנאי tnai
is always in my own interest, so maybe implicitly it's you give
me 200 dollars, implicit and I agree to accept it. Whereas if
the תורה Torah says you have the right to buy something back,
you know, maybe the תורה Torah is fundamentally giving that right to
the original owner and he is the one empowered and he has
that right even, you know,
against the guy's will. Like who knows exactly, there could be different
rules here. Anyway, but the גמרא’s Gemara understanding, it sounds like from
הלל's Hillel case that without הלל, Hillel, buying it back against his
will would not have worked, which would mean that we should say
the same here, that the normal rule is against somebody's will does
not work.
Okay, מכדי אצטריכא ליה להלל לתקוני נתינה בעל כרחו דהויא לה נתינה?
Michdi itztricha lei l’Hillel l’takuni nethina ba’al korcho de’havya lei nethina? Right.
מכלל דבעלמא נתינה בעל כרחו לא הויא נתינה? M’klal d’be’alma nethina ba’al
korcho lo havya nethina? Normally it doesn’t count. And רש״י Rashi says,
if you look at רש״י Rashi to answer what Michael said, מכלל
דבעלמא נתינה בעל כרחו לא הויא נתינה, m’klal d’be’alma nethina ba’al korcho
lo havya nethina, רש״י Rashi says, לגבי גט איסורא הוא לא תיקן
הלל. legabei get issura hu lo tikan Hillel. Not only did he
what
historically was he not מתקן metaken in our case, but also you
can’t make a תקנה takana by גט, get, right? Because you know
you’re dealing with a person’s personal status and married and divorced, it’s
not just like a money issue. Okay, now so that’s saying that
הלל’s Hillel basic thing, that’s assuming that the cases would have the
same הלכה halacha and assuming that what הלל’s Hillel תקנה takana was
needed for was because the guy would have refused to accept it.
Of course that wasn’t the case. The case wasn’t the guy was
there refusing to accept it, the case was the guy was running
away.
So מתקיף לה רב פפא ואי תימא רב שימי בר אשי, matkif
lah Rav Pappa v’i teima Rav Shimi bar Ashi, ודילמא כי אצטריכא
ליה לתקוני הלל שלא בפניו? v’dilma ki itztricha lei l’takuni Hillel shelo
befanav? Maybe הלל’s Hillel תקנה takana was the fact that the guy
wasn’t present, he couldn’t find him.
אבל בפניו בין מדעתו בין בעל כרחו הויא נתינה, Aval befanav bein
m’da’ato bein ba’al korcho havya nethina, right? Because actually you could actually
say that’s not just a possibility, you could say if it’s true
that נתינה בעל כרחו nethina ba’al korcho doesn’t work, then why did
the guy have to run away? Let him just stand around and
say I refuse to accept. Now תוספות Tosafot explains, no, that would
have been embarrassing, you know, to refuse to accept the guy’s trying
to use the power the תורה Torah gave him, it is his
house from a year ago. So you’re running away to save yourself
from embarrassment of refusing to accept. But רב פפא’s Rav Pappa saying
maybe not. Maybe from הלל Hillel you see that you could have
given it בעל כרחו. ba’al korcho. And the only thing הלל Hillel
had to deal with was that the guy wasn’t physically present. And
so therefore and so maybe the general rule is, assuming the cases
are the same, maybe the general rule is that בעל כרחו ba’al
korcho works.
ואיכא דאמרי אמר רבא V’ika d’amri amar Rava that that’s exactly how
the conversation began. That רבא Rava said, מתקנתו של הלל הרי זה
גיטך על מנת שתתני לי מאתים זוז ונתנה בין מדעתו בין בעל
כרחו הויא נתינה. Mi’takanato shel Hillel harei zeh gittech al menat shetitni
li matayim zuz v’natnah bein m’da’ato bein ba’al korcho havya nethina. That
actually רבא Rava started exactly with that point. From הלל Hillel you
see that a giving against somebody’s will does work. וכי
אצטריכא ליה להלל לתקוני שלא בפניו אבל בפניו בין מדעתו בין בעל
כרחו הויא נתינה? V’ki itztricha lei l’Hillel l’takuni shelo befanav aval befanav
bein m’da’ato bein ba’al korcho havya nethina? Because הלל’s Hillel only תקנה
takana was necessary because the guy wasn’t around. But it sounds like
if the guy was around physically present you could have given it
בעל כרחו. ba’al korcho. So it sounds like in general בעל כרחו
ba’al korcho works. So the גמרא Gemara says מתקיף לה רב פפא
ואי תימא רב שימי בר אשי, matkif lah Rav Pappa v’i teima
Rav Shimi bar Ashi, ודילמא אפילו בפניו נמי מדעתו אין בעל כרחו
לא. v’dilma afilu befanav nami m’da’ato in ba’al korcho lo. No, maybe
even had the guy stuck around you he would have been able
to refuse the money. והלל מאי דאצטריכא ליה תיקן? V’Hillel mai d’itztricha
lei tikan? And הלל Hillel was responding to the reality that the
guy wasn’t physically present. But אין הכי נמי, ein hachi nami, had
the guy been physically present and refused it, maybe that wouldn’t work
and maybe הלל Hillel would have had to make a תקנה takana
in that case as well. Maybe הלל’s Hillel תקנה takana was both
to address the בעל כרחו ba’al korcho and the שלא בפניו. shelo
befanav. So we don’t basically know.
whether in the case of the תורה Torah where it says you
can buy it back, does that mean even against somebody's will, and
we don't know, you know, and we don't know in our case
when the husband makes a תנאי, tnai, whether the נתינה בעל כרחה
nesina ba'al karcha works or not. But again logic would dictate that
I mean you could argue both ways but I think that the
simple logic would dictate that in the case of the תורה, Torah,
the תורה's Torah empowering the original owner, so tough luck if the
guy doesn't want to go along with it. He has the right
to buy it back. Whereas in the case when the husband makes
a תנאי, tnai, it's my תנאי. tnai. So if it's my תנאי,
tnai, you know, and I then it's only if I agree, it
means if you give it to me and I'm willing to accept.
Okay, that would have been the logic. תוספות Tosafot makes a way
you could have argued the reverse. Anyway, it's interesting that the גמרא,
Gemara, the only question in the גמרא Gemara is what was הלל
Hillel focusing on, not whether fundamentally the two cases are similar or
not. Yes, Michael.
Michael has his handza up.
The giving something to a בית דין beis din
does not count as giving it to him, right? I mean in
this הלל Hillel case, but generally, right?
If you and I engage...
if you and I engage in a loan and
then, you know, and whatever it is, I have thirty days to
pay you back, I can't just go to local בית דין beis
din and that would count, right?
Right, I mean there might be similar some similar types of תקנות
takanos in some cases but the general answer is correct. You would
have Now תוספות Tosafot also deals with a case about whether when
you pay back a loan can you do it בעל כרחו. ba'al
karcho. And he sort of indicates that the like I want I
I have the hundred dollars you lent me and I'm giving it
to you and you're saying no, I'm not gonna take it. So
I'm gonna you know so I'm just if I go ahead and
I stick it in your pocket I say tough luck, I'm paying
it back, I'm done with you. You know, do you have a
right to say I refuse to take it back and the loan
isn't paid? So there it seems like you know that the basic
הלכה halacha is I have a right to do בעל כרחו, ba'al
karcho, like there's a reality of a debt, I'm giving you the
money, there's an objective fact that you have your money back, like
it's the end of the סיפור. sippur. Can
you keep saying that I don't want it is not considered מחילה
mechila of the loan? No no no, it's like I don't want
to accept here, like the joke. The joke is you know two
guys are sitting on a like walking down a street, I heard
the joke originally sitting on a subway, whatever, walking down a street
and a guy comes to them and says like you know stick
up, you know says give me all your money. So he says
hey Frank, here's the $200 I owe you. So anyway, alright. Anyway
that might be already a case that's no longer their money. Anyway,
okay, let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. Yes.
Does the גמרא Gemara end with a question on הלל, Hillel, מה
איצטריך למתקי? mai itztrich lematkei?
No, maybe הלל Hillel was responding to the reality. He was מתקין
matkin what he needed to be מתקין. matkin. The current reality was
that the guy wasn't physically present. But maybe the תקנה takana was
not just about being physically present, maybe it was also about the
בעל כרחו. ba'al karcho. Just because the reality was was that the
guy wasn't present, you can't prove that the תקנה takana was only
about the need for the guy to be present. The תקנה takana
might also have been about the need for the guy to accept
it willingly. Okay. I see.
מה איצטריך למתקי. mai itztrich lematkei.
Right. Okay. אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן.
Amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rabbi
Yochanan. Now we're going to deal with הלכה. halacha. כל מקום ששנה
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל במשנתנו, kol makom sheshana Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
bemishnasenu, whenever רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel appears in
the משנה, Mishna, in any משנה, Mishna, הלכה כמותו, halacha kemoso, we
rule like him, חוץ, chutz, the only exceptions are ערב, arev, there's
a משנה Mishna about ערב, arev, okay, in a totally different גמרא,
Gemara, וצידן, v'Tzidan, ah,
this is וצידן. v'Tzidan. So צידן Tzidan is a story in צידן
Tzidan that a person
said על מנת שתתני לי את אצטליתי. al menas shetitni li es
itzalisi. It's funny and so that we've been calling it צידן, Tzidan,
we've been calling it like you would have said איצטלית itzalis or
something but צידן's Tzidan a shorter word, easier to remember. ערב וצידן
וראיה אחרונה. arev v'Tzidan v'raya achrona. There's a discussion in court if
somebody basically sort of says you know has given is given a
certain time to produce his evidence. So there's two debates in the
משנה, Mishna, so about somebody producing evidence. So the we don't rule
like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel in this second
debate regarding producing evidence in a משנה Mishna over in סנהדרין. Sanhedrin.
Okay,
אחרונה achrona is not describing the nature of the proof, it's the
second appearance of the second debate of around proofs that appear in
the משנה. Mishna. Okay, anyway so בקיצור bekitzur we don't rule like
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel in our משנה. Mishna.
תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, which is what the גמרא Gemara referred to
earlier. הרי זה גיטך והנייר שלי אינה מגורשת. harei ze gittech vehaniyar
sheli aina megureshes. Okay, if somebody says here's the גט get but
I'm keeping the paper, she's not מגורשת megureshes because then she doesn't
get any physical object, she hasn't actually taken possession of a physical
גט. get. על מנת שתחזירי לי את הנייר מגורשת. al menas shetachziri
li es haniyar megureshes. On the condition you return me the paper,
she's divorced. So the גמרא Gemara says מאי שנא רישא ומאי שנא
סיפא, mai shna reisha u'mai shna seifa, which is such a bizarre
question. What do you mean מאי שנא? mai shna? In the first
case he didn't give her anything. In the second case he gave
it to her and there's a condition she has to meet. Now
רש"י Rashi says and it's pretty clear from the גמרא Gemara but
it's such a bizarre גמרא, Gemara, that maybe the גמרא Gemara is
assuming that על מנת al menas is not כמעכשיו. k'me'achshav. Although the
גמרא Gemara said earlier that pretty much everybody says that על מנת
al menas is מעכשיו, me'achshav, here the גמרא Gemara is assuming that's
not true. So if על מנת al menas means it only takes
effect when the condition is met, so think what happens. Here's the
גט get and it'll take effect not only if you give me
back the paper, but if you give it to me, but if
and when you give it back to me. So why does that
work? When it's given back, she no longer is holding onto the
גט. get. Okay, everybody get it? So if על מנת al menas
does not mean מעכשיו, me'achshav, yeah, everybody with me here? No? Hello?
I'm just thinking about the...
I don't think it's אקשי, akshi, I think it's you didn't give
her the physical object. You have to take possession of the physical
object. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says מאי שנא רישא מאי שנא
סיפא mai shna reisha mai shna seifa assume that it only takes
effect when it's given back. So the גמרא Gemara says מאי שנא
רישא מאי שנא סיפא. mai shna reisha mai shna seifa. אמר רב
חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda, הני לאו רבן שמעון בן גמליאל היא hani
lav Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel hi דאמר תיתי לו את דמיה. de'amar
titee lo et dameha. Oh, so rather than saying על מנת כמעכשיו,
al menas kime'achshav, we say it's רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel that says by the איסטלית istelis you can just give
the money. So here too, even though it'll only take effect when
the גט get is given back, she can choose not to give
the גט get back but to give back its value. Give back
the value of I don't know, something written on a piece of
parchment. What value does a גט get have?
So this would be wrong, they don't פסקן pasken like him in
the end.
Well, right. But that's at least the ברייתא, braisa, that would be
the explanation of the ברייתא. braisa. דאמר תיתי לו את דמיה. de'amar
titee lo et dameha. So הכא נמי אפשר דמפייס ליה בדמי. hacha
nami efshar de'mifayes lei bidmei. Maybe she can appease him with money.
Now that's interesting, appease him, because until now it sounded like according
to רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, he's entitled to
give the money, he doesn't have to agree to it. Maybe it
gets back to that whole question of על כרחו. al karcho. Okay,
but anyway, but here too maybe the money counts as a substitute.
All right. So מתקיף לה אביי, matkif lah Abaye, אביי Abaye asks
on this, אימא דרבן שמעון בן גמליאל, eima de'Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel,
היכא דליכא בעיני. heicha de'leisa be'einei. Wait a minute. When did רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel say that money can count
as a substitute? If it not actually if you don't have the
original object. Then he's willing to say there's no alternative, we can
you know the thing isn't there, this represents the thing. היכא דאיתא
בעיני, heicha de'isa be'einei, here the גט get is still around, מי
אמר? mi amar? Even רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
would not say that money could count as giving back of the
גט. get. אלא אמר אביי, Ela amar Abaye, so it's so that's
why we brought this in because we tried to explain that it
makes sense according to רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel,
that you don't have to give the גט get back. But that
didn't work. So we still want to figure out why does this
work if you have to give the actual physical גט get back,
and presumably על מנת al menas is not מעכשיו me'achshav and it
only takes effect when the גט get is given back. So the
גמרא Gemara is going to have a very interesting series of explanations
why this doesn't work, all based on the same principle that the
תנאי tnai was not formulated correctly. So yes.
What's the implication of she returns the גט get then what happens
what's the implication of her evidence that she's divorced?
Well, if she can get the בית דין beis din to write
a to write up you know something an אישור ishur or something
that right or she could have witnesses that see the גט get
was given, right, yeah.
Does נייר niyar mean parchment? It means papyrus.
That's actually true. נייר niyar actually does mean papyrus. Okay. So now
the גמרא Gemara says, okay. מתקיף ליה רבא, matkif lei Rava, I'm
sorry I skipped a line. אלא אמר אביי, Ela amar Abaye, אביי
Abaye says, you know why here it works even though the תנאי
tnai would mean it only takes effect when it's given back?
אמר אביי רבי מאיר היא, Amar Abaye Rabbi Meir hi, דאמר בעינן
תנאי כפול, de'amar be'inan tnai kaful, והכא לא כפליה לתנאיה. v'hacha lo
kafla l'tna'ei.
So like this גמרא Gemara makes me want to scream because גמרא
Gemara says you know why here it's different? It's different because yeah
the תנאי tnai isn't binding. When he says על מנת שתחזירי לי
את הגט. al menas shetachziri li es haget. Why is the תנאי
tnai not binding? Because רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says that any תנאי
tnai you have to double the תנאי. tnai. Meaning like by בני
גד ובני ראובן Bnei Gad uBnei Reuven that says אם יעברו בני
גד ובני ראובן את הירדן im ya'avru bnei gad u'bnei reuven es
hayarden you know ונתתם להם אחוזה בארץ כנען, v'nasatem lahem achuza b'eretz
kena'an, ואם לא יעברו בירדן, v'im lo ya'avru bayarden, ואם לא יעברו,
v'im lo ya'avru, then they get it you know בארץ כנען. be'eretz
kena'an.
That's symbolic logic. Right.
So anyway so there you have to basically both say the if
this happens so if the condition is met this will happen and
if it's not met that will happen. Right, because as Dov says
just because you say if P then Q does not mean if
not P then not Q. So therefore you have to spell out
both possibilities. That's what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says מכלל לאו אתה
שומע הן, miklal lav ata shome'a hen, which is correct from a
from a propositional logic perspective. Anyway, the reason though this גמרא Gemara
makes me want to scream is, so גמרא Gemara says yo you
know why it works? It works because the תנאי tnai doesn't work.
So if the תנאי tnai worked then only when you gave back
the גט get she wouldn't be divorced she wouldn't have the גט.
get. But we forget the תנאי. tnai. The תנאי tnai is invalid
because it wasn't doubled. So the point is like we've been learning
for all this time about על מנת al menas this על מנת
al menas that על מנת al menas this and what you're really
telling me is all those cases according number one according to רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir would not work because the תנאי tnai wasn't doubled,
number one, which is okay maybe. And now you have another innocent
ברייתא braisa that you have a hard time explaining, so you're going
to say oh in this ברייתא braisa the על מנת al menas
doesn't work because he didn't double the תנאי tnai and we're dealing
with רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. And the whole point of the ברייתא
braisa is to contrast הנייר שלי שתחזירי לי את הנייר. haniyar sheli
shetachziri li es haniyar. And what you're really saying is it's not
really contrasting those two. Those two really have the same equivalent effect
that she's not מגורשת. megureshes. What we're really doing is tell you
a completely separate הלכה halacha that because you didn't formulate the תנאי
tnai correctly the תנאי tnai isn't binding. So it's like it's so
bizarre to bring that in and use that to explain this ברייתא.
braisa. It's the opportunity
methodologically perhaps, because in this specific case of גיטין Gittin where you
want to adjudicate it by being able to throw out the תנאי,
tnai, you now have a
principle...
Yeah, that's a huge חידוש chiddush to think that you could just
sort of like the בית דין Beis Din could at their discretion
say, oh, here we're going to פסקן pasken like רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir as opposed to not. That's not what the גמרא Gemara is
saying. The גמרא Gemara is saying the author of this ברייתא braisa
is רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Now you agree with me. Anyway, yeah,
exactly. Anyway, but it's completely bizarre. A, it means according to רבי
מאיר, Rabbi Meir, all the על מנת al mnat we've been dealing
with until now are not good, which maybe the answer is אין
הכי נמי. ein hachi nami. And number two is that was not
the point of the ברייתא. braisa. But anyway, because it's having this
hard time with the ברייתא, braisa, you say the problem is we
throw out the תנאי. tnai. הא רבי מאיר היא דאמר בעינן תנאי
כפול והכא לא כפליה לתנאיה, Ha Rabbi Meir hi de'amar beinan tnai
kaful ve-hacha lo kaflia letnaye, you didn't double it. מתקיף לה רבא,
Matkif lah Rava, רבא Rava challenged this. טעמא דלא כפליה לתנאיה, Tama
d'lo kaflia letnaye, you're telling me the problem was he didn't double
the תנאי. tnai. הא כפליה לתנאיה לא הוי גיטא, Ha kaflia letnaye
lo havi gitta, but if he did double the תנאי, tnai, the
תנאי tnai would be binding and therefore it wouldn't be a good
גט get because it would only take effect when it was given
back. So מכדי, michdi, he says, I got another reason why the
תנאי tnai wasn't good. כל תנאי מהיכא גמרינן להו? Kol tnai me-heicha
gamrinan lehu? Where do we learn all תנאים tnaim from? מתנאי בני
גד ובני ראובן, Mi-tnai bnei Gad u-bnei Reuven, from the תנאי tnai
of the בני גד bnei Gad and the בני ראובן bnei Reuven
about getting their נחלה nachala in עבר הירדן. Ever HaYarden. מה התם
תנאי קודם למעשה אף כל תנאי קודם למעשה. Mah hatam tnai kodem
l'maaseh af kol tnai kodem l'maaseh. There, the תנאי tnai preceded the
act. It says אם יעברו ונתתם את האחוזה, im ya'avru v'natatem et
ha-achuzah,
ואם לא יעברו. ve-im lo ya'avru. So first you mention if the
condition is met, then you will get it. Okay, תנאי קודם למעשה,
tnai kodem l'maaseh, אף כל תנאי קודם למעשה. af kol tnai kodem
l'maaseh. לאפוקי הכא דמעשה קודם לתנאי. L'afukei hacha d'maaseh kodem l'tnai.
When he says הרי זה גיטך על מנת שתחזירי לי את הנייר,
harei zeh gittech al mnat she-tachziri li et ha-niyar, he didn't say
על מנת שתחזירי לי את הנייר, al mnat she-tachziri li et ha-niyar,
or I'm sorry, על מנת שתחזירי לי את הנייר, al mnat she-tachziri
li et ha-niyar, it's all that phrasing. Okay, לאפוקי הכא דמעשה קודם
לתנאי. L'afukei hacha d'maaseh kodem l'tnai.
So basically it's like, oh, if we're going to talk about ways
you can throw this out if you need to use these formal
rules, then there's more way, there's a lot of ways. So רש"י
Rashi says that רבא's Rava's point was that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
who needs doubling, that's debated. That's a debate whether you need doubling,
but everybody agrees you need these other conditions. And רבא Rava wants
to say it's פסול passul for these other reasons. תוספות Tosafot says
it's not true. All these things or a lot of these things
are just רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir's position. But nevertheless, what what רבא
Rava is saying is, oh, you want to talk about what's called,
this is called in the literature, משפטי התנאים. mishpetei ha-tnaim. You want
to talk about all of the formal rules of תנאים? tnaim? So
why are you only mentioning the double? There's another problem here about
the formal rules of תנאי. tnai. Now according to תוספות, Tosafot, that
might just be שיטת רבי מאיר. shitas Rabbi Meir. So but רבא
Rava is still saying like we can pull a lot of things
here that are not satisfying those formal rules. And you don't have
here תנאי קודם למעשה. tnai kodem l'maaseh. You said הרי זה גיטך
harei zeh gittech and then you said על מנת שתחזירי לי את
הנייר. al mnat she-tachziri li et ha-niyar. Now by the way I
should mention that there is, I mean there are huge debates in
ראשונים. Rishonim. There's a whole like work of the of the of
the ראב"ד Raavad and the בעל המאור Baal HaMaor and whatever about
like how to going through all of these formal rules of the
תנאים. tnaim. Who which תנא tanna says them? How do which way
do we פסקן, pasken, whether you need them or not need them?
Which cases do you need them for? And what is actually the
תנאי tnai demanding? So the question Dov raised a second ago which
is I was telling you רש"י Rashi which is the simplest way
I think to read it, is תנאי קודם למעשה tnai kodem l'maaseh
is about formulation. It's just which order the words come out of
your mouth. אם im if you do it then I'll give you
you know if if על מנת שתחזירי לי את הנייר הרי זה
גיטך, al mnat she-tachziri li et ha-niyar harei zeh gittech, right? All
the cases by the way beforehand were the opposite, הרי זה גיטך
על מנת. harei zeh gittech al mnat. Okay, but some ראשונים Rishonim
say that תנאי קודם למעשה tnai kodem l'maaseh doesn't mean that. It
means that the תנאי tnai has to be satisfied
before the מעשה maaseh takes effect. Now how that would actually work
by a גט, get, I'm trying to think because if you say
like if you do this then I'll give you the גט, get,
I
guess that would sound like it would just undermine the מעכשיו-ability me-achshav
of things to work, right? Because if it's תנאי... tnai I don't
know, I don't remember, I'd have to actually go review it. But
there is some discussion, there are some ראשונים Rishonim that say תנאי
קודם למעשה tnai kodem l'maaseh is not just an issue of formulation,
it's an issue about the actual effect that the תנאי tnai has
to be satisfied somehow before. Which if if they can't say that
completely because then it would completely rule out מעכשיו-ability me-achshav for things
to work.
Yeah, that's back to רש"י Rashi that wouldn't pass.
Right, right, right. So that's why רש"י, Rashi, we'll just take the
simple explanation. I don't remember the specifics. רש"י Rashi says it's an
issue of formulation.
I think there's a biblical Hebrew equivalent to על מנת. al mnat.
You mean just other than אם. im. Right.
Like what you're going to say... Right. וזה... וזה. v'zeh יעקב's Yaakov's
תנאי tnai with הקדוש ברוך
הוא.
HaKadosh
Baruch Hu.
אם יהיה אלקים
עמדי,
Im yihyeh
Elokim
imadi, that's the אם. im. The only question is when he switches
from the תנאי tnai.
to the to the thing but the אם im is the תנאי.
tnai. והיה ה' לי לאלקים, Ve-hayah Hashem li l'Elokim, right? And then
והיה v'hayah that then is good.
Yeah, but the אם im is the תנאי. tnai. Anyway okay. אלא
אמר רבא משום דמעשה קודם לתנאי. Ella amar Rava mishum d'maaseh kodem
l'tnai. If you want a reason to throw it out, you don't
need the doubling reason, the lack of doubling, it's because he mentioned
the act, הרי זה גיטך, harei zeh gittech, before the תנאי. tnai
מתקיף לה רב אדא בר אהבה. Matkif lah Rav Adda bar Ahava.
So רב אדא בר אהבה Rav Adda bar Ahava asked, טעמא דמעשה
קודם לתנאי, Tama d'maaseh kodem l'tnai, that you think the problem is?
I'm going to tell you another problem. Okay, הא תנאי קודם למעשה
Ha tnai kodem l'maaseh according to... So wait, you think if you
said the תנאי tnai first, על מנת שתתני לי את הגט, al
m'nat shetitni li es haget, it would have worked? לא, Lo, בגיטין
b'Gittin the תנאי tnai would be binding, and because the תנאי tnai,
would be binding, the גט get would work. You understand? By throwing
out the תנאי, tnai, it makes the גט get effective. We don't
throw out the גט, get, we throw out the תנאי, tnai which
makes the גט get effective, right? So he says: So wait, you
think that if you switch the order formulating it, it would be
a good תנאי tnai and therefore not a good גט? get? מכדי,
Michti, I'll give you another reason why the תנאי tnai wasn't good.
כל תנאי מהיכא גמרינן להו? Kol tnai mehecha gamrinan lahu? Where do
we learn out all תנאים? tnai'im? מתנאי בני גד ובני ראובן. Mi'tnai
Bnei Gad u'Bnei Reuven. From בני גד ובני ראובן. Bnei Gad u'Bnei
Reuven. מה התם תנאי בדבר אחד ומעשה בדבר אחר. Mah hatam, tnai
bidavar echad u'maaseh bidavar acher. There the תנאי tnai was in one
thing: You have to go fighting. And the fulfillment of the תנאי
tnai was another thing: You get עבר הירדן. Ever HaYarden. אף כל,
Af kol, that everything else,
also תנאים, tnai'im, the fulfillment of the תנאי tnai has to be
external, something other than the act itself that we're talking about that
we want to be binding. לאפוקי הכא, l'afukei hacha, to exclude this
case,
התנאי והמעשה בדבר אחד. hatnai ve'hamaaseh bidavar echad. The מעשה maaseh is
הרי זה גיטך. harei ze gittech. The תנאי tnai is you have
to do something with the גט. get. So, no, I'm sorry, you
have to follow these formal rules, and you can only make a
תנאי tnai on something that's not related to the actual act itself.
Right. Now, רש"י Rashi seems to say you can just not have
a תנאי tnai about the גט get at all. Like you couldn't
say: הרי זה גיטך harei ze gittech על מנת al m'nat that
you hold the גט get in your mouth for two
hours. No, it's
תנאי ומעשה בדבר אחד. tnai ve'maaseh bidavar echad. תוספות Tosafot says, no,
no, no, what it means is, דבר אחד davar echad does not
just mean it happens to be about the same thing and the
same object. It means that the actual doing of the תנאי tnai
is a contradiction, is סותר soter the מעשה, maaseh, would require, right.
In a way the תנאי tnai has to be fulfillable. If the
only way you can fulfill the תנאי tnai is by, there's no
way you can fulfill the תנאי tnai. and make the מעשה maaseh
work, so obviously we throw out the תנאי. tnai, The תנאי, tnai
there's no way it could have been fulfilled. Okay, so that's the
way תוספות Tosafot explains that requirement.
Like הרי זה גיטך harei ze gittech if you were to write
my name George instead of Dov,
something like that.
Now, does that סותר soter the actual, like in other words, פוסל
passel the גט get itself?
No, what do you mean? No, it wouldn't פוסל passel the גט.
get. הרי זה גיטך harei ze gittech is the giving of the
גט. get. I mean, it's hard to imagine what another case would
be about that. I mean, the other case would be as long
as על מנת al m'nat means 'when', you could say על מנת
ש, al m'nat she, yeah, I don't know, we'd have to figure
it out. But anyway, but for רש"י Rashi it's just that it
relates to the same object. For תוספות, Tosafot, it's that any תנאי
tnai, that makes the, that its
fulfillment makes the whole thing you're trying to do not good, obviously
isn't the תנאי, tnai because the whole point of a תנאי tnai
is to make the thing good. So you can't create a תנאי
tnai that its effect would make the thing not good, would make
the act not good. אלא אמר רבא
בר אבא ela amar Rava bar Abba mishum דתנאי ומעשה בדבר אחד.
d'tnai ve'maaseh bidavar echad. The reason the תנאי tnai. is thrown out
is because it all relates to the same thing, either the same
object or because it contradicts the thing you're doing. רב אשי אמר,
Rav Ashi amar, so we have a whole list of reasons, which
of course is not at all פשט pshat in that ברייתא, braisa,
but it's basically, it gives us an opportunity to talk about what
are the laws of תנאים tnai'im according to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir,
maybe according to everyone. So the question becomes, I want to point
you before we turn on, before we continue, to the תוספות Tosafot
דף ע"ה עמוד א'. Daf Ayin Heh Amud Aleph. Like how do
we פסקן? pasken? Do we פסקן pasken you need all these תנאי,
tnai. all these formal rules? Are these all only according to רבי
מאיר? Rabbi Meir? Or some of them according to רבי מאיר? Rabbi
Meir. So if you take a look at תוספות, Tosafot, לאפוקי. l'afukei.
The first wide line. Do people see where I
am on דף ע"ה עמוד א'? Ayin Heh Amud Aleph? Yes. So
תוספות Tosafot says: ונראה דהלכה כרבי מאיר, Venireh dehalacha k'Rabbi Meir, דבעינן
תנאי כפול, d'ba'inan tnai kaful, דשמואל ורבא בסמוך סברי כוותיה, de'Shmuel ve'Rava
b'samuch savri kevatei, וכל הני דמתניתין. ve'chol hani d'matnisin.
So how about all our משניות Mishnas that say: על מנת al
m'nat שתתני לי מאתים זוז, shetitni li matayim zuz, על מנת, al
m'nat,
all those על מנת al mnats of our משניות? Mishnas? אם מתי,
im meisi, all those things? איירי בתנאי כפול אף על גב דלא
פירש. Airy bitnai kaful, af al gav d'lo peireish.
Even though the משנה Mishna didn't explain it, we're going to have
to go back and say that all those cases we're dealing with
a תנאי כפול. tnai kaful. דהכי מוקי לה לקמן בברייתא, Dehachi moki'leha
lekaman be'braisa, דכפולה דתנאי אף על פי שלא פירש. d'kafula detnai af
al pi shelo peireish.
ובכל על מנת שבש"ס, Uvechol al m'nat shebaShas, anytime you find anywhere
in the ש"ס Shas that the גמרא Gemara says על מנת al
m'nat and assumes that it works,
כגון על מנת שתחזירהו לי דאתרוג וכיוצא בו, kigon al m'nat shetachzireihu
li de'esrog ve'chayotze bo, like by the אתרוג esrog when you give
על מנת להחזיר, al m'nat l'hachazir,
בת כפילות, bat kifelus, we have to assume that all those cases
is when you were כופל kofel the תנאי. tnai, ובכל מקום בעינן
תנאי כפול. Uvechol makom ba'inan tnai kaful. And then he has one
case where we don't, where it's something that has to do with
just איסור issur and not ממון, mamon, etc., etc. And then if
you look at the end of this תוספות, Tosafot, which is like
so crazy because you have all these סוגיות sugyas with על מנת
al m'nat this and על מנת al m'nat that, and now we're
going to say that all of them need these laws of תנאי
כפול, tnai kaful, and what about all these other things: תנאי קודם
למעשה, tnai kodem l'maaseh, והן קודם ללאו, v'hen kodem l'lav, which is
why a lot of other ראשונים Rishonim, either disagree in terms of
how we פסקן pasken or say that the cases that require these
formal rules are very narrowly defined. In particular, there's a, and well
let me read the last line of תוספות Tosafot because that'll frame.
what those cases might be that you don't need these rules. So
if you go to the end of this תוספות, Tosfos, he says
like this: ואמר רבינו יצחק, V'omar Rabbeinu Yitzchak, two lines above where
it says אלא, Ela, the next תוספות, Tosfos, okay? ואמר רבינו יצחק,
V'omar Rabbeinu Yitzchak, הא דנקיט פטומי מילי, ha d'naki ptumei mili, I'm
sorry, וג' עניינים, v'gimel inyanim,
I'm sorry,
after that, you see after the like where it says the line
starts אפילו רבנן דרבי מאיר, afilu rabbanan d'rabbi meir, right,
about ten lines from the bottom? וג' עניינים יש. V'gimel inyanim yesh.
There are three categories. ויש מקומות דבעינן תנאי גמור V'yesh m'komot d'ba'inan
tnai gamur
that you need all the formal rules of a תנאי. tnai דרבי
מאיר תנאי כפול, D'rabbi Meir, tnai kaful, which would include a תנאי
כפול tnai kaful according to רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir ויש מקומות דלא
בעינן אלא גילוי דעת. V'yesh m'komot d'lo ba'inan ela giluy da'as.
There's sometimes where it's not about a תנאי, tnai it's about showing
what your basic intent is. ויש מקומות דאפילו גילוי דעת לא בעינן.
V'yesh m'komot d'afilu giluy da'as lo ba'inan. You don't even have to
articulate your intent. Your intent is assumed. ובפרק האיש מקדש מפורש, u-v'ferek
ha'ish mekadesh meforash, I'll explain that in another גמרא. Gemara. Okay, which
basically means the following.
The basic way to explain it is, usually a תנאי tnai is
seen as
the basic approach in the ראשונים, Rishonim sort of which תוספות Tosfos
is outlining, and then the question is just how do you define
which cases are which, is that when something is not central to
my desire to do the act. I really want to marry this
woman, I want to divorce this woman, I want to buy this
house, okay? But okay, I've got some side thing that I want
to be satisfied. But fundamentally is do you know do I want
to do it with or without that side thing? Yes. In principle
I really want to do it. But I'm in a position to
make some demands, I'm going to make some demands. Okay, so that's
seen as the תנאי tnai is fundamentally external. The action is really
taking place by itself. The דעת da'as is fundamentally there. So you
want this external תנאי tnai, to come in and like stop the
works, it has to be a very formally done and follow very
formal rules. Okay, that's when we need the formal rules. However, if
something is more central to my דעת, da'as, like I say, okay,
you know, I'm like here, I'm not right now like we're looking
for like new couches for the house. So I like I like
leather couches and you I see you can easily get tricked, you
know, what's the fake leather and the real leather. So let's say
what the heck, I bought this couch from a guy and he
promised me it was real leather and I said, fine, I'm buying
it from you, but only on the condition it's real leather and
I'm going to get it checked afterwards, right? So I don't need
משפטי תנאים. mishpetei tna'im. Like I didn't want to buy it if
it wasn't real leather. Right, so that's the type of a thing
where that's like fundamental to my דעת da'as to do the transaction
where you don't need these formal rules. It's just a question of
I didn't want to do it if those weren't the circumstances. And
then the third category is I don't even have to articulate it.
It's so obvious. Okay. So, you know, somebody goes ahead and I
don't know, you know, whatever it is. Like, you know, buys a
car and they don't say I it better be that it's not
that you know that that it hasn't that you've removed the engine
from it. Okay? Or something like that. You know, whatever it is,
something that or the better case, I mean the case that the
גמרא Gemara has, which isn't that obvious, is that the guy basically
said, you know, said, okay, we're making עליה, aliyah, we bought the
plane tickets, we're ready to go, we're having a yard sale, we're
selling all of our stuff. Okay, and they sold all the stuff
and then it was like oh my god something just happened we
have to cancel our plans we can't make עליה. aliyah. So how
about all the how about what they just sold in their yard
sale? So the גמרא Gemara basically says, well all of those transactions
are בטל, batel, because clearly he was only doing it, you know,
because he was planning on making עליה. aliyah. Now he never said
when he actually sold the couch, I am doing this because I'm
assuming that my עליה aliyah plans are going through. Okay, but that
was clear to everybody. It was clear from context. Okay, so anyway,
so those are the three types of things. When the תנאי t'nai,
is fundamentally external to the דעת, da'as, that's might be when you
need the laws of תנאים. tna'im. When it's not really an external
תנאי, t'nai, it's fundamentally a you know a basic thing that you
need to be present, which is why you're assuming why you're agreeing
to do it in the first place, it's central to your דעת,
da'as, but then you still need to articulate it, otherwise it's דברים
שבלב אינם דברים. d'varim she'blev einam d'varim. And then there's a third
case, which is called דברים שבלב כל אדם, d'varim she'blev kol adam,
which is you don't even need to articulate it. It's just obvious
to everybody that that's your the assumptions that you're working with. Okay,
so that's a very important conceptual categories there, yes.
So so so first of all, it seems to me, I don't
know what you think about this, but this תוספות Tosfos is an
amazing example of the fact, maybe this is obvious, but you can't
separate like legal methodology, like in פסיקה, psika, from how you decide
for whatever reason to read the פשט p'shat of the
גמרא. Gemara. Right, תוספות Tosfos reads רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir, back into
all that all those three categories and derives from that fundamentally a
method a legal methodology. Here's how we adjudicate cases of תנאים. tna'im.
Okay, there's a typology...
Well, but he starts from the fact that he feels that the
גמרא Gemara פוסקין paskens רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir so that forces him,
yeah.
But you don't have to read it like you can, right, it's
very interest like in other words, there's an organic relationship between a
me a legal methodology and the reading of the פשט.
p'shat. Right, right, I think
so
too.
Right, right. Right. I would be obligated to give it back?
According to,
you know, maybe it depends, like maybe, I mean, I don't know,
but there's a גמרא Gemara that is that does say that, okay.
So, yeah.
And I was going to say in some cases
האי גוונא דזבין לנכסיה אדעתא למיסק לארעא דישראל, hai gavna d'zavin l'nichsei
adaita lemeisak l'ara d'Yisrael,
you know, and in the end he wasn't able to make עליה
aliyah and says, you know, מקח טעות. mekach ta'ut. So I don't
know that what happens if it's I don't know what to say.
You know, you might want to make a distinction between things that
are like that are like
trivial pieces like if you're selling buying little junk at the yard
sale, like, you know, you didn't expect to run after everybody or
whatever. If I actually if I actually bought, right, the guy's, you
know, dining room set, the table and the the sofas, like, no,
excuse me, like give them back, you know. So, yeah.
And I was thinking in terms of the modern commerce, so I
don't know how that would work. Right.
Right. I mean that can work in like a small community type
of a thing. Right. Right. Yeah. Right. Okay, so now let's take,
let's continue the גמרא. Gemara. ע״ו עמוד ב. Ayin-vav amud bet. רב
אשי אמר הא מני רבי היא דאמר דאמר רב הונא אמר רב,
Rav Ashi amar ha mani Rabbi hi d'amar d'amar Rav Huna amar
Rav, this is so how again, going back to what the difference
of על מנת al menat שתהא מעכשיו, shet'he mi'achshav, where the גמרא
Gemara thinks that the problem is because how does it work when
you give back the גט, get, it can't take effect. So finally
we say the most obvious thing we should have said from the
first minute.
הא מני רבי היא דאמר רב הונא אמר רב, Ha mani Rabbi
hi d'amar Rav Huna amar Rav, should be אמר רבי amar Rabbi
כל האומר על מנת
כאומר מעכשיו דמי. kol ha'omer al menat k'omer mi'achshav dami. What was
the problem? על מנת, Al menat, you give me back the גט,
get, but it takes place, takes effect as of now, right? That
was the easiest answer. You guys got yourself in such a, you
put yourself in such a corner because you said why did it
take effect, how could it work when you give back the גט,
get, you're no longer holding onto it, okay? It took place, takes
effect from the moment it's given on the condition that the condition
is met. Okay. התקין שמואל בגיטא דשכיב מרע. Hiskin Shmuel be'gita d'shchiv
mera. שמואל Shmuel made a תקנה takkanah in a גט get of
a שכיב מרע shchiv mera that if he's giving a גט get
and he wants it to take effect, you know, on the condition
he dies, that he should say the following. אם לא מתי לא
יהא גט ואם מתי יהא גט. Im lo meisi lo yehei get
v'im meisi yehei get. So he's introducing the תנאי כפול, t'nai kaful,
okay? Does this prove that he פוסק paskens like רבי מאיר that
you need a תנאי כפול t'nai kaful or is he just doing
it because since it's a גט get case Shmuel is often stringent?
Yeah, and you know, you might want to just eliminate any questions,
any doubts, you know, as long as we're establishing a a text
maybe we want to make it satisfy everybody.
You can't ask him anyway.
Right, so I don't know. That's right. Anyway, so he says if
I don't die it won't be a גט get and if I
do die it will be a גט, get, so it's a תנאי
כפול. t'nai kaful. So the גמרא Gemara says why not do the
reverse order?
ולימא אם מתי יהא גט ואם לא מתי לא יהא גט? Velayma
im meisi yehei get v'im lo meisi lo yehei get? So the
גמרא Gemara says no, לא מרחק איניש פורענותא לנפשיה. la marku inish
puranut l'nafshei.
A person doesn't want to, you know, it's עין הרע, ein hara,
you don't want to start by saying, we don't want to make
a נוסח nusach that forces you to to start by saying if
I die. God willing I won't die, and then it won't be
a גט. get. If God forbid I die, then it'll be a
גט. get. Okay. ולימא לא יהא גט אם לא מתי. Velayma lo
yehei get im lo meisi. So why not just, so why do
you have to do the double? Just say it won't be a
גט get if I don't die. Okay. I don't know why the
גמרא Gemara just say why not say it will be a גט
get if I do die, but okay, because now we're assuming that
you don't want to say the if I die part. So גמרא
Gemara says no, בעינא be'ina or anyway, בעינא
תנאי קודם למעשה. be'ina t'nai kodem lema'aseh. So why do you start
by saying אם לא מתי לא יהא גט? im lo meisi lo
yehei get? Why not say לא יהא גט אם לא מתי? lo
yehei get im lo meisi? I'm sorry, I misexplained the question. Why
do you first say if I don't die, if I do die?
Why don't you first say it will be a גט get if
I die, it won't be a גט get if I don't? So
here again we're saying no, you need תנאי קודם למעשה. t'nai kodem
lema'aseh. This by the way is very clear, the תנאי קודם למעשה
t'nai kodem lema'aseh is about the formulation, right? It's just the order
in which you say the words. So here again you
see we're in need of
תנאי כפול, t'nai kaful, תנאי קודם למעשה, t'nai kodem lema'aseh, we're seeming
like you
need all of these rules of תנאים. t'naim. So מתקיף לה רבא.
Maskif lah Rava. So רבא Rava challenges. מכדי, Michdi, one minute, let's
take a look. כל תנאי היכא גמרינן מתנאי בני גד ובני ראובן.
Kol t'nai heicha gamrina mi'tnai B'nei Gad u'Vnei Reuven. מה התם, Ma
hasham,
now we're going to introduce a new, we didn't have enough rules
about תנאי, t'nai so we're going to have a new one. מה
התם הן קודם ללאו. Ma hasham hen kodem l'lav. The yes comes
before the no, right? It says, if you do this then you
will get עבר הירדן, Ever HaYarden, and if not you won't. So
you first have to say the yes part of the תנאי, t'nai
if the תנאי tnai. is fulfilled here's what's going to happen. אף
כל Af kol אף אוקי הכא דלאו קודם להן. af-ukei hacha d'lav
kodem l'hen. Here because you didn't want to give an עין הרע,
ein hara, you started by saying the no. If I don't die
it won't be. No, a תנאי tnai, has to start with if
this condition is
met. Then you say,
oh and by the
way, אם לא מתי לא יהא גט. Im lo masi lo yehei
get. So, because then,
because the first part lets you not open up with an עין
הרע, ayin hara, and then you have to do the if I
die and if I don't die so that you have the הן
קודם ללאו. hein kodem l'lav.
First part's not really part of the תנאי.
tnai Meaning, right, you could really say like, God, like,
God willing,
I'll live, I'll live a hundred and twenty and there'll be no
need for any of this. If, God forbid, I die, it'll be
a גט, get, if I don't, it won't be. Okay. So אם
לא מתי לא יהא גט, Im lo masi lo yehei get, לא
מקדמי אינש בפורענותא, lo makdmi inish b'puranusa, you don't want to start
by saying something bad. אם מתי יהא גט אם לא מתי לא
יהא גט, Im masi yehei get im lo masi lo yehei get,
but you need the הן קודם ללאו, hein kodem l'lav, you need
the yes before the no. So this גמרא Gemara certainly ends that
at least by the תקנה takana of שכיב מרע, shachiv meira, they
satisfied all these משפטי התנאי. mishpatei hatnai. Whether that's the הלכה halacha
in general or not that you need those things is not clear.
The ראשונים discussion on all these תנאים tna'im that you mentioned before,
the מאור הגדול, Maor Hagadol, whatever, is on this סוגיא sugya like
in גיטין? Gittin?
No, I mean they're like of separate קונטרס kuntres on some of
this stuff. Yeah. Okay, הרי זה גיטך על מנת שתשמשי את אבא.
Harei zeh gitayich al m'nas she-teshameshi es abba. Next משנה. Mishnah. Here's
your גט, get, but you know what? Like, you still have to
take care of my father. My father's ill, he's been at the
house or whatever, you've been so good to him. So I'm divorcing
you, but you still have to be there to take care of
him. Okay, so he says על מנת שתניקי את בני, al m'nas
she-teniki es beni, or, you know, because in the general הלכה halacha
is that the, that the father gets custody of the kids in
the גמרא, Gemara, I mean later הלכה halacha switched it that it's
for the, it's the decision is based on the best interests of
the child. But anyway, but okay, I'm divorcing you, but you still
got to come home, come, you know, come back every day and
nurse our infant.
So in those things, those תנאים tna'im are binding. And כמה היא
מניקתו? kamah hi menikaso? For what duration does she have to nurse
the child? שתי שנים, shtei shanim, two years, meaning until he's two
years old. רבי יהודה אומר שמונה עשר חודש. Rabbi Yehuda omer shmonah
asar chodesh. Okay, so that's the condition. So one thing is, even
though you didn't say an amount of time, implicitly by nursing it's
until the child's a particular age.
Now, מת הבן או שמת האב, meis haben o she-meis ha-av, let's
say the son dies or the father dies, so הרי זה גט,
harei zeh get, it's still good.
רש"י Rashi says that that means if she actually did some form,
if she did one act of nursing, one form of taking care
of the father, then she satisfied the תנאי, tnai and obviously the
תנאי tnai is only in effect as long as the child is
alive
or until he reached an age, or as long as the father
was alive. So תוספות Tosafos says if that's true, then that's so
obvious that's not the case of the משנה. Mishnah. תוספות Tosafos says
no, the חידוש chiddush of the משנה Mishnah is the father or
the infant died before she did anything. So she did not have
a chance to attend to the father, she did not have a
chance to nurse the child. Nevertheless, the תנאי tnai is satisfied because
it's sort of like what the גמרא Gemara before said: it was
all done to achieve a certain הנאה, hana'ah, a certain benefit, right?
Remember like when it rained and you didn't need the act being
done? So the person died, there's no need for this service to
be done in this context. So that's like the תנאי tnai is
fulfilled. That is a big חידוש. chiddush. You said that you have
to nurse the child, and she never nursed the child, and the
תנאי tnai is fulfilled because there's no longer a child to be
nursed, so there's no need for it anymore. Okay, הרי זה גיטך
על מנת שתשמשי
את אבא שתי שנים, Harei zeh gitayich al m'nas she-teshameshi es abba
shtei shanim,
two years. Explicitly says the duration. על מנת שתניקי את בני שתי
שנים, Al m'nas she-teniki es beni shtei shanim, and in that case
מת הבן, meis haben, the son died, or the father died, or
שאמר האב, she-amar ha-av, or the father said, אי אפשר שתשמשני, ee
efshar she-teshamisheni, I do not want her to attend to me, שלא
בהקפדה, she-lo b'kapdah, and he's not doing that because she did anything
wrong to him, it's not her fault, right, he's just, I don't
want her to attend to me. In that case אינו גט, eino
get, it's not her גט, get, because you explicitly said two years.
So even though it's like there's no, or what the child, forget
the, we'll worry about the father saying I don't want in a
minute, but the baby died, the father died, so there's like nothing
to be done. Doesn't matter. He said two years. When he says
the amount of time, if there's no, well, that's true too, if
there's no amount of time, then it means as needed. Okay? When
there's an amount of time, then you have to do the amount
of time. You didn't do the amount of time. It's no good.
Okay? So it's the same if the father refuses: I demanded X,
and I did not, there's no implicit as needed. Once the time
is given, then that time is required, whether needed or not. Now,
אמר רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, amar Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, and remember
we just said a minute ago we פסקן pasken like רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel in our משנה, Mishnah, כזה גט,
kazeh get, that does work actually. כלל אמר רבן שמעון בן גמליאל,
Klall amar Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, he said a principle: כל עכבה
שאינה הימנה, kol akavah she-einah heimena,
any withholding, any non-fulfillment that's not her fault, הרי זה גט, harei
zeh get, it's good. So meaning that's why it said שלא בהקפדה,
she-lo b'kapdah, if... If she offended the father and the father said
I refuse to have you take care of me then it's not
a גט get then the reason it's not fulfilled is her fault
but if it's out of her hands okay then
then it's not which does which seems to not only be because
it could be argued that we always read in the as-needed as
implausible as implicit
but you could also type of read it as a question about
יש אונס yesh ones right? Remember the יש אונס yesh ones discussion?
Like I'm ready to do it, there's something external that's making it
impossible. That counts further like I did it, you know? So it's
not because there's an implicit as-needed part about it, it's just like
a you know what would be if what Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
would be if she was you know she was seized and thrown
into prison not because she did anything wrong because of the גוים
goyim okay you know what I mean like the Romans just decided
arbitrarily to throw her into prison. So would it which she so
he would say that's not her fault it's a good גט. get.
So it's not because we read the as-needed into the תנאי tnai
like we did originally it's more like a יש אונס בגיטין yesh
ones b'gittin right? If he if it's not her fault then then
it's then considered like the תנאי tnai? is met.
And then it's like I think we even had this before in
that example.
I will sell you my truck you could take it now on
the condition that this season you deliver me a ton of corn
from your fields and there's a hurricane and everything is washed out.
Yeah although that's a little different because again that gets you how
much is it an external תנאי tnai or a central part of
the transaction. But yeah some of those issues before about this יש
אונס yesh ones right. Okay so that's interesting. Is Rabban Shimon saying
because of like the first part of the משנה mishna that we
always read the as-needed in or is he just saying no if
it's אונס ones it's אונס. ones. Okay let's look at the גמרא.
gemara. וממאי דבעי כולי האי Umimai d'baei kuli hai do you really
need
all that amount of time? The משנה mishna says like two years
you know for the kid even if no time was given. It's
implicit until nursing means until he's two years old that's implicit. ורמינהו
U'reminhu הניקתו יום אחד שימשתו יום אחד הרי זה גט henikato yom
echad shimshato yom echad harei zeh get that if he says if
you take care of my father or nurse my child all you
need to do is do it for one day you didn't say
how much time I did it once end of story. So how
come the ברייתא braita says that and the משנה mishna says you
need to do it till he's two years old? So אמר רב
חסדא לא קשיא הא רבנן והא רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Amar Rav
Chisda lo kashya ha rabbanan v'ha Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel it's the
old Rabbis and Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. מתניתין רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
Matnitin Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel who is Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel who
said by the cloak. Remember the Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel by the
cloak? He said the cloak could also mean the money. So here
there he was a קולא. kula. But here he's going to be
a חומרא chumra because there basically Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel is not
hyper-precise about reading it. Like to say like you said nurse your
child I nursed him one day goodbye. Okay that's being hyper-precise. So
who's hyper-precise about reading the תנאי? tnai The רבנן rabbanan because they
say cloak means cloak. So there the Rabbis who were strict here
they're going to be lenient. The גמרא gemara is saying it's not
an issue of strict or lenient. It's an issue of do we
read the תנאי tnai always extremely precisely or not. So הא רבנן
ha rabbanan what says like this יום אחד. yom echad. אמר רב
חסדא לא קשיא הא רבנן והא רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Amar Rav
Chisda lo kashya ha rabbanan v'ha Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. מתניתין רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל Matnitin Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel who is not precise
who doesn't say you just read it in a hyper-precise way. So
nursing means nursing as long as he needs it until he's two
years old. וברייתא U'braita that says one day counts רבנן rabbanan the
Rabbis who say we always read it in the hyper-precise way or
hyper-literal way. So גמרא gemara says one minute היי מני דסיפא רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל הוי מכלל דרישא לאו רבן שמעון בן גמליאל הוי.
Hai mani d'seifa Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel hovei miklal d'reisha lav Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel hovei. You can't say that because Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel is introduced in the end of the משנה. mishna. So the
opening of the משנה mishna is not Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. So
גמרא gemara says אלא ברייתא רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Ella braita Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel. Fine let's get away from our more conceptual issue
about hyper-literal versus non-hyper-literal and we'll just go to the other thing
about lenient or strict. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel is more liberal in
assuming when a תנאי tnai is considered to be met. He took
the money instead of the cloak. So if he's more prepared to
give a generous interpretation that the תנאי is met so the so
if you say nurse for one day so if you say nurse
she said okay I nursed for one day fine. Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel says any you know any
approximation I'm more liberal in interpreting that the תנאי is met. So
one day would count.
He המיקל בתנאי. hameikel b'tnai. מתניתין רבנן Matnitin rabbanan and the משנה
mishna is the Rabbis. The Rabbis are more precise and not precise
but they are not as you know willing and as liberal to
say that that counts as satisfying. We really go what did he
mean when he said nurse even though he said nurse what he
really meant was nurse until the child needs it. Okay and I
guess we'll end here we'll pick up tomorrow to see other ways
of reading reading
the difference between the משנה mishna and the ברייתא. braita.